Guide to the Randolph Linsly Simpson African-American Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Randolph Linsly Simpson African-American Collection
1728-1991
1850-1970
JWJ MSS 54
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
30
(94 boxes) + 6 broadsides, 5 artwork
The Randolph Linsly Simpson African-American Collection consists chiefly of photographs dating from circa 1850 to 1970, but also includes printed illustrations, original artwork, documents and printed ephemera that provide a record of black history in the United States for the period circa 1770 to 1970. The focus is on African-American subjects, but the collection also includes the work of black photographers, as well as images of white men and women, many of whom were associated with the abolitionist movement. Collected with a broad scope, the images provide information about individuals at all socio-economic levels and include people of all ages and gender. They represent the work of professional photographers in various regions of the United States and some European countries, and the image formats present in the collection reflect the development of photographic processes, beginning with Daguerreotypes and extending through mid-twentieth century formats.
Simpson, Randolph Linsly, 1927-1992
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase from Swann Galleries, Inc., 1995 on various funds.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Separated Materials
A substantial portion of the printed material received with this collection, including books, newspapers, pamphlets, and sheet music, was removed for separate cataloging. Simpson's item numbers were not retained in the catalog records for these items, but his ownership is noted. Printed items that duplicated existing holdings were not retained by the library.
Associated Materials
The Amistad Center for Art & Culture at the Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art holds a related collection acquired from R. L. Simpson in 1989.
Randolph Linsly Simpson (1927-1992)
The collector Randolph Linsly Simpson was born on June 1, 1927, and grew up both in Rochester, New York, where his father, Charles A. Simpson, worked in banking, and in Northford, Connecticut, at the family home of his mother, Eunice Hall Linsly Simpson. After graduating from the Harley School in Rochester in 1945, he served two years in the U. S. Navy, and later worked as a voice teacher. Simpson lived the latter part of his life at the Linsly homestead in Northford.
The Linslys were among the first to settle Northford, Connecticut, and many generations of the family attended Yale, from Noah Linsly, Yale 1791, to Simpson's older brother Josiah J. L. Simpson, Yale 1948. Simpson's interest in the material record of black history in America was apparently inspired by his family's abolitionist history, and by the proximity of his childhood home on Mount Hope Avenue in Rochester to the cemetery in which Frederick Douglass is buried.
Simpson's large collection of images, artifacts, and other memorabilia documenting the African-American experience drew a great deal of interest during his lifetime. In January, 1984, NBC television aired a one-hour special on the collection, "Blacks: Present and Accounted For." A portion of the collection was exhibited at the Connecticut Governor's Mansion in February 1985 and at the Wadsworth Atheneum in February 1987. In 1989 the Wadsworth Atheneum, through the then titled Amistad Foundation, purchased approximately 7,000 items from Simpson.
Simpson died on January 6, 1992.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Visual Material. II. Printed Material. III. Artifacts.
Scope and Contents
The Randolph Linsly Simpson African-American Collection consists chiefly of photographs dating from circa 1850 to 1970, but also includes printed illustrations, original artwork, documents, and ephemera that provide a record of black history in the United States for the period circa 1770 to 1970. The focus is on African-American subjects, but the collection also includes the work of black photographers, as well as images of white men and women, many of whom were associated with the abolitionist movement. Collected with a broad scope, the photographs represent the work of professional photographers in various regions of the United States and some European countries, and the formats present reflect the development of photographic processes, beginning with Daguerreotypes and extending through mid-twentieth century formats. The collection contains images of Frederick Douglass, Martin Luther King, Marcus Garvey, W. E. B. DuBois, Paul Lawrence Dunbar, Sojourner Truth, Louis Armstrong, and Joe Louis, as well as of George Washington and Abraham Lincoln, among other highly recognized figures. It also includes a large number of photographic portraits of lesser-known African-American subjects, including politicians, bankers, athletes, entertainers, domestic servants, emancipated slaves, and soldiers. Among the few documents in the collection is a ship manifest listing one slave aboard the "Telegraph," out of Providence, Rhode Island, in 1811. The collection also includes three-dimensional artifacts such as commemorative spoons, lapel buttons, and a plaster bust of Booker T. Washington.
Note that there is some overlap between the series, and that images can be found not only in Series I. Visual Material, but in Series II. and III. as well. In Series II. Printed Material, several printed documents and booklets include illustrations or postcards. In Series III. Artifacts, images are often incorporated into objects.
Abolitionists; African American photographers; African Americans -- Pictorial works; African Americans -- 19th century -- Portraits; African Americans -- 20th Century -- Portraits; Ambrotypes (photographs); Cabinet photographs; Card photographs (photographs); Daguerreotypes (photographs); Ephemera (general object genre); Photographic prints; Snapshots; Stereographs; Tintypes (prints); Simpson, Randolph Linsly, 1927-1992
- Series I. Visual Material
  Arrangement
  Series I. is organized into fifteen subseries: Daguerreotypes, Ambrotypes, Tintypes, Cabinet Photographs, Cartes de Visite, Stereographs, Later 19th Century Photographs, 20th Century Photographs, Postcards, Photographic Postcards, Albums, Novelty Photographs, Prints, Paintings and Drawings, and Film. Within each subseries, material is arranged by the collector's item numbers.
  Scope and Contents
  Visual Material consists chiefly of photographic images but also includes a small number of prints, paintings, and drawings. The photographs consist of nineteenth-century formats including Daguerreotypes, ambrotypes, tintypes, card photographs, stereographs, and larger albumen prints, as well as twentieth-century formats and genres including silver gelatin prints, photomechanical prints, snapshots, and news service photographs. The earlier photographs are predominantly portraits, but later images include outdoor scenes and documentary images of laborers at work in fields, factories, or shipyards, for example. Portrait subjects include slaves and servants, actors and musicians, athletes, military personnel, politicians, and leaders in the abolitionist and civil rights movements. The series also includes prints dating from the late eighteenth century, including engravings, etchings, and lithographs. The image subjects of the prints range from scenes of slavery to portraits of political figures to patriotic illustrations, including World War I posters promoting the military contributions of African Americans.
  - DAGUERREOTYPES
    Daguerreotypes, dating from approximately 1850 to 1865, include the work of prominent African-American photographers James Presley Ball, Sr., Cincinnati, Ohio; Augustus Washington, Hartford, Connecticut; and C. J. Goodridge, York, Pennysylvania. Among the sitters are the banker Erasmus Cartwright and members of his family, and abolitionists William Lloyd Garrison, George Thompson, Wendell Phillips, and Gerrit Smith.
    - J.P. Ball, Sr., Cincinnati. Young man seated, left arm resting on book on table. Daguerreotype, half plate, circa 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      Item #1
    - Attributed to Southworth and Hawes, Boston. William Lloyd Garrison, George Thompson and Wendell Phillips, seated at a table. Un-cased Daguerreotype, quarter plate, circa 1850-51 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Item #2
    - Unknown photographer, Baltimore[?] Hattie Cartwright Powell (1796-1881), Mother of Erasmus Cartwright; portrait of lady seated with white bonnet and hands folded in lap. Daguerreotype, sixth plate, circa 1855 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      This and following two items are of a single family during the slavery period.
      Item #3
    - Unknown photographer, Baltimore[?] Portrait of man, left elbow on table. Daguerreotype, sixth plate, circa 1855 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Erasmus Cartwright, Founder and President of the United Negro Mechanics Bank of Wilmington, Delaware (1818-1871).
      Item #4
    - Unknown photographer, Baltimore[?] Rufus G. Cartwright, Son of Sally Cartwright Williams (1822-18??), portrait of a man playing fiddle. Daguerreotype, sixth plate, circa 1855 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Traveled as musician with medicine show. Played fiddle and piano forte.
      Item #5
    - Unknown photographer Bust-length portrait of Gerrit Smith; white man facing left. Daguerreotype, sixth plate, circa 1855 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Portrait of Gerrit Smith (1797-1874) prominent wealthy abolitionist, supporter of John Brown and Frederick Douglass. Earliest known portrait of subject without a beard.
      Item #6
    - Augustus Washington, 135 Main Street, Hartford, CT. Half-length portrait, white lady facing front, folded hands, white bonnet. Daguerreotype, sixth plate, circa 1855 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Item #7
    - Unknown photographer Seated lady holding fan and Daguerreotype. Daguerreotype, sixth plate, circa 1855 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Item #8
    - Augustus Washington, Hartford, CT. Half-length portrait of a white man facing forward. Daguerreotype, sixth plate, circa 1850 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Recto case: "Wolfert's Roost" Verso case: "Washington Gallery 136 Main St., Hartford"
      Item #9
    - Unknown photographer Three quarter length portrait, man seated holding book, right arm resting on column. Daguerreotype, ninth plate, 1858-59 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      "Peterson a barber in Naugatuck 1858-59, a friend of my father, Wm. Levick[?]" From manuscript notes in case.
      Item #10
    - Unknown photographer Lady in gingham dress facing forward. Daguerreotype, hand-colored, ninth plate, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Item #11
    - J. White & Co., Providence, RI Bust-length portrait of young man facing forward. Daguerreotype, ninth plate, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Business card, inside case, verso Daguerreotype: "J. White & Co's 25 cent AMBROTYPES and Daguerreotypes..."
      Item #12
    - C.J. Goodridge, York, PA. Half-length portrait of white man, daguerreotype left hand, right elbow on book. Daguerreotype, sixth plate, circa 1850 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      C.J. Goodridge and family were not only prominent black photographers from York, but their studio and home were stations used on the underground railroad.
      Item #12 a.
    - McClees and Germon, Philadelphia, PA A post-mortem portrait; young man three quarter length on a background of a white knit shawl with tassels. Quarter plate, Daguerreotype, circa 1855 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Item #2076
    - Unknown photographer A sixth plate daguerreotype post mortem portrait of the same subject as Item #2076. Sixth plate, daguerreotype, circa 1855 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Item #2077
    - Unknown Photographer Three quarter portrait: black woman wearing bandanna seated with white child on lap. Quarter plate, daguerreotype, circa 1855 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Item #2078
    - Unknown photographer Double portrait: black "nanny" seated on left with white child seated on right. Black woman holds small ball. Sixth plate, daguerreotype, tinted, circa 1855 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Item #2079
    - Un-numbered Items, undated (Box 2, Folder 18-26)
      Includes 9 unidentified daguerreotypes.
  - AMBROTYPES
    Ambrotypes, dating from circa 1855 to 1865, include images of the abolitionist and congressman Joshua R. Giddings, as well as those of an unidentified female black musician and "Uncle Moreau," a North Carolina slave noted for his scholarship.
    - Unknown photographer Half-length portrait, seated young lady, holding nine string banjo. Ambrotype, sixth plate, circa 1865 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      Item #13
    - Unknown photographer Bust length portrait, young woman, with lace collar. Ambrotype, sixth plate, circa 1860 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      Item #14
    - Unknown photographer Double half-length portrait, black woman holding white child in lap. Ambrotype, sixth plate, circa 1850 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      In pencil inside back of case: "Carolina Wright and servant." Collector's note: "Beaufort, S.C., from source."
      Item #15
    - Unknown photographer Half-length portrait of a young man, seated with hand on table. Ambrotype, sixth plate, circa 1860 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      Plate stamped: "Cary 371, Canal St"
      Item #16
    - Unknown photographer Half-length portrait, seated lady with lace collar and fur cuffs. Ambrotype, sixth plate, circa1860 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Item #17
    - Unknown photographer Three quarter length portrait, seated elderly lady with fancy dress and white bonnet, holding handkerchief and glasses. Ambrotype, sixth plate, circa 1858 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Item #18
    - Unknown photographer Three quarter portrait, seated young black lady, summer dress. Ambrotype, sixth plate, circa 1860 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Verso, second image, three quarter portrait, seated white lady in summer dress. [Packet is currently sealed; do not open.]
      Item #19
    - Unknown photographer Half-length portrait of young boy seated in chair, big bow tie. Ambrotype, sixth plate, circa 1860 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Item #20
    - Ball and Thomas, 120 West 4th Street, Cincinnati, OH Cameo portrait of young white girl. Ambrotype, cameo, sixth plate, circa 1855 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      Item #21
    - N.M. Knights, Young man wearing straw hat. Ambrotype, ninth plate, circa 1860 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      Printed photographer identification on verso of Ambrotype.
      Item #22
    - Unknown photographer Half-length portrait, seated lady with much jewelry. Ambrotype, ninth plate, circa 1859 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Item #23
    - Unknown photographer Half-length portrait, young girl seated with hands in lap. Ambrotype, ninth plate, circa 1860 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Item #24
    - Unknown photographer Half-length, seated young lady, polka dot dress and gold jewelry. Ambrotype, ninth plate, circa 1855 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Item #25
    - Unknown photographer Half length formal portrait of "Uncle Moreau"; elderly man seated wearing headwrap, suit; left elbow rests on newel, cane in right hand. Ambrotype, circa 1850 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      Subject identified in pencil on paper mounted underneath ambrotype inside back of case, "'Uncle Moreau' a slave of great notoriety, of North Carolina, a scholar who once wrote me a letter in Arabic & sent me his picture, a sketch of his life. Was in the Congregationalist, also the American Missionary."
      Item #2049
    - Unknown photographer Oval portrait of young girl wearing gingham dress and gold tinted jewelry. Ninth plate, Ambrotype, circa 1860 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      Item #2080
    - Unknown photographer Half length portrait of Jessie Morley; young man seated, with long hair curled on one side, wearing a three piece suit with flowing black tie. Sixth plate, Ambrotype, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
      "Jessie Morley" in pencil inside back of case. Acquired from family in Old Saybrook, Connecticut.
      Item #2089
    - Un-numbered Items, undated (Box 4, Folder 43-60)
      Includes 18 unidentified ambrotypes.
  - TINTYPES
    More than one hundred tintypes date from approximately 1850 through 1900. The majority of images in this format depict middle class individuals who pose in professional studios. However, the tinypes also docment exterior scenes and include images of workers including surveyors, teamsters, and railroad porters. Images of Civil War soldiers in uniform include a full-plate portrait of armed black soldiers shown with a backdrop of cannon, drum, and Union flag. An undated miniature depicts three nuns.
    Related Archival Materials note
    See Also: Item #2173, family photo album including tintypes
    - Unknown photographer Bust length portrait of Joshua R. Giddings. Melainotype, ninth plate, circa 1855 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      Earliest abolitionist member of Congress; fellow-boarder with Lincoln in Washington, D.C.; prominent in the Amistad decision in Congress.
      Item #26
    - Unknown photographer Full length portrait, young man standing, hand on bible on table Cased tintype, quarter plate, circa 1865 (Box 5, Folder 62)
      Item #27
    - Unknown photographer Exterior group portrait: survey crew of six: four white, two black. White man sits on instrument case in front, hat and notebook in hand studying maps, the rest stand in a line behind him with tripods, rods, various other tools of trade. Cased tintype, quarter plate, circa 1880 (Box 5, Folder 63)
      Item #28
    - Unknown photographer Half-length portrait, young boy seated with flower in lapel. Cased tintype, sixth plate, circa 1870 (Box 5, Folder 64)
      Item #29
    - Unknown photographer Bust portrait, elderly lady. Cased tintype, sixth plate, circa 1868 (Box 5, Folder 65)
      Item #30
    - Unknown photographer Full length portrait, man seated in Union uniform. Cased tintype, sixth plate, circa 1875 (Box 5, Folder 66)
      Item #31
    - Unknown photographer Three quarter portrait, young soldier seated, in Union uniform with kepi; tents (possibly painted backdrop) in background. Cased tintype, sixth plate, circa 1863-84 (Box 5, Folder 67)
      Item #32
    - Unknown photographer Three quarter length portrait, young solder seated, kepi and cigar. Cased tintype, sixth plate, circa 1865 (Box 5, Folder 68)
      Item #33
    - Unknown photographer Full length portrait, young lady standing against pedestal, with fancy hat. Cased tintype, sixth plate, circa 1875 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      Item #34
    - Unknown photographer Three quarter portrait, young Civil War soldier in kepi. Cased tintype, ninth plate, circa 1865 (Box 5, Folder 70)
      Item #35
    - Unknown photographer Three quarter length portrait, soldier with bass drum, holding sticks. Cased tintype, gutta percha case, ninth plate, circa 1870 (Box 5, Folder 71)
      Item #36
    - Unknown photographer Bust portrait, young girl, cap with tassel. Cased tintype, ninth plate, circa 1870 (Box 5, Folder 72)
      Item #37
    - Unknown photographer Half-length portrait, young boy. Cased tintype, ninth plate, circa 1870 (Box 5, Folder 73)
      Item #38
    - Unknown photographer Half-length portrait, young boy wearing straw hat. Cased tintype, ninth plate, circa 1869 (Box 5, Folder 74)
      Item #39
    - Unknown photographer Group portrait, family of five, Cased tintype, half plate, circa 1875 (Box 6, Folder 75)
      Item #40
    - Unknown photographer Bust portrait, young boy with boutonniere. Cased tintype, gem tintype case, sixteenth plate, undated (Box 6, Folder 76)
      Item #41
    - Unknown photographer Full length group of three; black woman seated with white child in lap, white boy stands with hand on her shoulder. Cased tintype, quarter plate, circa 1875 (Box 6, Folder 77)
      Item #42
    - Unknown photographer Three quarter portrait, young man, standing with hand on wooden post. Cased tintype, ninth plate, undated (Box 6, Folder 78)
      Item #43
    - Unknown photographer Full length portrait, young lady seated with bouquet of flowers. Cased tintype, sixth plate, circa 1875 (Box 6, Folder 79)
      Item #44
    - Unknown photographer Full length, two young men with straw hats, seated beside each other. Cased tintype, sixth plate, undated (Box 6, Folder 80)
      Item #45
    - Unknown photographer Full length portrait of young sailor. Cased tintype, gutta percha case, sixth plate, circa 1868 (Box 6, Folder 81)
      Item #46
    - Unknown photographer Full length portrait, young soldier wearing kepi. Cased tintype, sixth plate, circa 1868 (Box 6, Folder 82)
      Item #47
    - Unknown photographer Gem portrait, soldier with kepi. Cased tintype, ninth plate, circa 1870 (Box 6, Folder 83)
      Item #48
    - Studio unknown Full length portrait, lady standing with fur collar and muff. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1875 (Box 7, Folder 84)
      Item #49
    - Studio unknown Full length portrait; young girl standing by post. Tintype, circa 1875 (Box 7, Folder 85)
      Item #50
    - Studio unknown Three quarter portrait, young man seated with arm resting on chair. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1880 (Box 7, Folder 86)
      Item #51
    - Studio unknown Full length portrait; young lady standing by chair, white neck piece. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1890 (Box 7, Folder 87)
      Item #52
    - Studio unknown Three quarter length portrait, young lady with hat seated by newel post. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1870 (Box 7, Folder 88)
      Item #53
    - Studio unknown Bust portrait, young man wearing teamster's hat. Tintype, oval, paper mount, ninth plate, circa 1868 (Box 7, Folder 89)
      Item #54
    - Studio unknown Full length group portrait; five young ladies, two seated, three standing, all with hats, forest backdrop. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1880 (Box 7, Folder 90)
      Item #55
    - Studio unknown Half-length portrait, young woman in striped dress. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1875 (Box 7, Folder 91)
      Item #56
    - Studio unknown Full length portrait, woman standing by pedestal. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1890 (Box 7, Folder 92)
      Item #57
    - Studio unknown Half-length portrait, young man with gold watch chain and handkerchief in coat pocket. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1885 (Box 7, Folder 93)
      Item #58
    - Studio unknown Full length portrait, man standing behind balustrade, hand on newel post. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1885 (Box 7, Folder 94)
      Item #59
    - Studio unknown Full length portrait, seated boy with dog. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1870 (Box 7, Folder 95)
      Item #60
    - Studio unknown Half-length portrait, lady with white ruff, brooch, severe hair dressing. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1885 (Box 7, Folder 96)
      Item #61
    - Studio unknown Bust portrait, woman with "Afro" hair dressing. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1880 (Box 7, Folder 97)
      Item #62
    - Studio unknown Full length double portrait, two ladies holding hands, one standing in dark dress, one seated with arm on table in light dress. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1890 (Box 7, Folder 98)
      Item #63
    - Studio unknown Three quarter length portrait, lady standing in elaborate dress, brimmed straw hat with band. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1890 (Box 7, Folder 99)
      Item #64
    - Studio unknown Half-length portrait, seated young woman with tinted gold jewelry. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1880 (Box 7, Folder 100)
      Item #65
    - Studio unknown Full length portrait, man seated with cigar in hand, prominent watch chain, Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1885 (Box 7, Folder 101)
      Item #66
      "NATIONAL" on cap
    - Studio unknown Half-length portrait, man seated holding coat lapel; stickpin in other lapel. Tintype, sixth plate, circa 1885 (Box 7, Folder 102)
      Item #67
    - Studio unknown Oval portrait in paper face, young man with striped bow tie. Tintype, ninth plate, circa 1870 (Box 7, Folder 103)
      Item #68